Finding Aid for Hospitals (University of Michigan) records, 1875-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hospitals (University of Michigan) records 1875-2005
University of Michigan. Hospitals.
33 oversize volumes
1 oversize folder
158 linear feet
87196 Bimu C 500 2
The University of Michigan Hospital system has evolved and expanded since its inception in 1869. The various hospitals, such as the C.S. Mott Children's Hospital and W.K. Kellogg Eye Center, provide medical treatment to the Ann Arbor, Michigan area. The Hospitals records contain five series: Hospital Administration, Nursing, Committees/Councils, Patient Files, and Hospital Buildings. This collection includes meeting minutes, patient files, director files, correspondence, and more.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Hospital records (donor no. 2289 ) were acquired in several accessions beginning in 1966. A portion of the record group came from the University of Michigan Medical School (donor no. 647 ). In April 2000, 26.5 linear feet were added to the collection. In April 2015 Associate Director of Nursing records were added as a series (donor no. 2289 )
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The records are open to research except for these exceptions: Boxes 40-48 are closed except to the donors of the records; patient case records found in (but not limited to) boxes 2-9 are open after the researcher has read and signed the "Patient Record Access Agreement. Registration Books are closed.
The Hospital record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Patient/Client Records -- Boxes 2-9 and oversize volumes 2-33
Architectural Drawings -- Boxes 40-48
Executive Officers Records -- Boxes 130-132, 138-152.
University Hospitals Chronology
1869 A professor’s home on North University is converted into a small hospital (20-24 beds) for patients, becoming the first hospital controlled by a university medical school.
1875 Two pavilions are added to the existing hospital, for a total of 60 beds. The construction is made possible by state appropriation as well as funding from the city of Ann Arbor.
1889 Appropriations from the Michigan Legislature, combined with funding from the city of Ann Arbor allow for the construction of a new hospital, built on Catherine Street over the next two years.
1891 The new Catherine Street Hospital opens and is shared by the medical department and the homeopathic medical college. The homeopathic medical college moves to another location in 1900, with the vacated space taken over by University Hospital.
1903 The 75-bed Palmer Ward, one of the first children’s wards in the United States, opens in the Catherine Street Hospital.
1908 Jay B. Draper becomes hospital superintendent, serving until 1915. During his tenure, the hospital becomes responsible for its own finances, resulting in a surplus. The resulting complaints lead to the formation of a new Hospital Committee, created by Regental approval (January 1912), to oversee the hospital.
1910 The University opens Michigan’s first psychiatric hospital.
1924 Harley A. Haynes (M.D. 1902) is appointed director of the University Hospital and is one of the earliest to bring cost accounting to hospital administration.
1925 The Catherine Street Hospital is replaced by University Hospital (also known as Old Main Hospital), a 700-bed facility, built at a cost of $4.4 million.
1928 University Hospital offers the first physician training program in thoracic surgery.
1942 The University of Michigan Base Hospital (General Hospital No. 298) is organized and subsequently serves in England, France, and Belgium.
1950 Women’s Hospital opens as a 66,822 square foot facility. The Birth Center was one of the first facilities to offer single-room maternity care.
1955 The Child and Adolescent Psychiatric Hospital opens.
1969 C.S. Mott Children’s Hospital opens its doors, as the University’s first hospital devoted entirely to children. The 272,732 square foot facility houses 200 beds.
1972 The James and Lynelle Holden Perinatal Hospital is built, providing care for premature and critically ill infants.
1975 The Regents approve the Bylaws for the Executive Board of University Hospital.
1976 The W.K. Kellogg Eye Center, a 32-bed facility, is established, providing patient care, education and research in eye diseases.
1978 The Regents approve the creation of the Finance and Personnel Committee, which serves as a governing authority for financial matters and strategic planning.
1982 The University begins its Survival Flight program, a hospital-based airborne emergency medical service - the first in the state.
1986 The University Hospital and A. Alfred Taubman Health Care Center open. The 11-story hospital is nearly 1.8 million square feet in size and holds 550 beds. The A. Alfred Taubman Health Care Center, which houses 120 outpatient clinics. The conversion from Old Main into the new facilities takes place on Feb. 14.
1986 M-CARE, a University HMO plan is developed. As of the year 2002, it serves over 200,000 members in 14 counties, offering HMO, point of service, Medicare and Medicaid plans.
1990 The hospitals expand, adding integrated services for women and children in new space and renovated units in existing hospitals.
1995 Creation of Michigan Health Care Corporation, and University of Michigan Health System
1997 The University of Michigan moves its cancer and geriatrics clinical and research programs into the $88 million Cancer Center and Geriatrics Center Building.
1999 The Health System creates the Department of Emergency Medicine.
2001 The University of Michigan Health System establishes the nation's first Depression Center.
2006 Construction begins on the C.S. Mott Children's Hospital and Women's Hospital addition after receiving a $25 million grant from the Mott Foundation
2007 The University of Michigan Cardiovascular clinical building opens to provide support for heart, vascular, and stroke care patients.
2009 The Health System receives a $15 million gift from the Ted and Jane Von Voigtlander Foundation to begin construction on a new women's hospital.
2010 The new Brehm Tower at the W.K. Kellogg Eye Center opens, increasing the capacity of providing eye care to patients.
2011 The new C.S. Mott Women's Hospital and Von Voigtlander Women's Hospital opens. The Adult Emergency Department and Psychiatric Emergency area is expanded.
2012 A master affiliation agreement is signed with the Michigan hospitals of Trinity Health
2013 Ground is broken on a new outpatient center, the Northville Health Center. University of Michigan managed inpatient beds are opened in the Chelsea Community Hospital and Saint Joseph Mercy-Ann Arbor Hospital. The Cardiovascular Center is named in honor of Samuel and Jean Frankel.
Name Changes in Hospital Administration
During the early years of the University Hospital operation (1869-1874), the institution was entrusted to the care of janitors and matrons. In 1874, a house physician was placed in charge, beginning a series of different titles, ranging from steward, to superintendent and later, director. The list of early overseers is sketchy.
The University Hospital Board in Control was replaced by the University Hospital Executive Board in 1974.
In 1978, the Board of Clinical Directors was superseded by the Nursing Executive Committee
In 1982 the Planning Advisory Committee became the Public Advisory Board.
The Replacement Hospital Project was dissolved in June 1984 with the formation of the Vice Provost Advisory Board, under the administration of the Vice Provost for Medical Affairs.
In January 1989 the Hospital Executive Team became the Hospital Advisory Group.
In 1997 the U-M Board of regents approves "University of Michigan Health System" encompassing the Hospitals and Health Centers, Medical School, M-Care, and Michigan Health Corp.
The School of Nursing becomes a part of the University of Michigan Health System in 2008. All of the hospitals and many of the clinical units are transitioned into a computerized order entry system called UM-CareLink.
Hospital Superintendents / Directors
1869-1870 John Carrington -- Janitor and Steward
1874-1876 Robert J. Peare -- House Physician
1877- ? Alexander Maclean -- Hospital Superintendent
1888-1897 Joseph Clark -- Steward; Superintendent
1897-1900 Harry W. Clark -- Superintendent
1900-1908 E.S. Gilmore -- Superintendent
1908-1915 Jay B. Draper -- Superintendent
1912-1918 Hospital Committee; Reuben Peterson (Medical Director)
1915-1918 Robert Greve -- Superintendent (Temporary)
1918-1924 Dr. Christopher G. Parnall -- Medical Superintendent and Director
1924 Robert G. Greve -- Acting Director
1924-1945 Harley A. Haynes -- Hospital Director
1945-1969 Albert C. Kerlikowske -- Hospital Director
1969-1973 Edward J. Connors -- Hospital Director
1973-1974 David G. Dickinson -- Acting Director
1975-1985 Jeptha W. Dalston -- Executive Director
1985-1996 John D. Forsyth -- Executive Director
1996-2005 Larry Warren -- Executive Director
2006-2010 Douglas Strong -- Interim Director
2010-2014 Tony Denton -- Executive Director
2014- Shon Dwyer -- Executive Director
Summary Contents List
HISTORY AND SUMMARY INFORMATION
History of University Hospital by Reuben Peterson (Box 1)
Annual Reports, 1959-1968 of hospital departments (Boxes 24- 25)
Clippings, 1947-1970 (Boxes 25-26)
ADMINISTRATION
University Hospital Executive Staff Minutes, 1919-1940 (Box 27)
Hospital Executive Team (HET)/Hospital Advisory Group (HAG), 1988-1990 (Box 97)
University Hospital Board in Control, 1945-1974 (Boxes 27 and 51-52)
University Hospital Executive Board, 1974-1996 (Boxes 51-59, 79-81)
Replacement Hospital Project, 1970-1984 (Boxes 28-34 and 39- 50)
Clinical Delivery Systems Executive Committee (CDSEC), 1995-1997 (Boxes 84-85)
Clinical Delivery Systems Management Team (CDSMT)/Systems Management Team (SMT), 1995-1997 (Box 85)
Executive Committee on Clinical Affairs (ECCA), 1975-1995 (Boxes 86-92)
University Hospital Executive Board, 1984-1996 (Boxes 93- 97)
Executive Director's Advisory Council, 1980-1994 (Boxes 93- 94)
Executive Director's Council, 1987-1995 (Boxes 94-96)
Executive Director's Forum, 1993-1994 (Box 96)
Hospital Executive Team (HET), 1998 (Box 97)
Hospital Advisory Group (HAG), 1988-1990 (Box 97)
Bole/Forsyth Staff Meetings, 1995-1996 (Box 97)
DIRECTOR AND OTHER ADMINISTRATORS
Director's Correspondence, mostly 1934- 1943 (Boxes 10-13)
Director: John D. Forsyth, 1983-1996 (Boxes 102-106)
Director: Jeptha W. Dalston, 1985 (Box 106)
Associate Director: John Zugich, 1970-1977 (Boxes 19- 23)
Assistant Director: Arlene Howe, 1962-1980 (Boxes 35- 37)
Associate Director, Health Sciences Relations: Marsha A. Bremer, circa 1983 (Box 39)
Associate Director for Nursing (formerly Chief of Nursing), 1969-1982 (Boxes 74-78); 1951-2002, bulk 1976-1996 (Boxes 138-152)
HOSPITAL COMMITTEES
Hospital Committee Minutes, 1892-1914 (Box 1)
Planning Advisory Committee, 1977-1981 (Boxes 60- 61)
Public Advisory Board, 1982-1985 (Box 62)
Joint Conference Committee, 1978-1986 (Boxes 63-65, 81- 82)
Clinical Chairmen's Council, 1979-1982 (Boxes 65-67)
Joint Staff (University Hospital - Medical School), 1976-1984, 1993-1994 (Boxes 67-71, 97)
Finance and Personnel Committee, 1978-1985 (Boxes 71-73, 82)
Medical Staff Standing Committees (MSSC), 1974-1993 (Boxes 99-100)
Medical Staff Quarterly Meetings, 1982-1988 (Box 100)
MISCELLANEOUS AND COLLECTED MATERIALS
Historical Documents (Box 1)
Time Reports, Personnel Assignments, etc.(Box 1)
Case Records (various departments and clinics) (Boxes 1- 9)
Pediatrics cases, record book, 1885-1888 (BOUND VOLUME (OUTSIZE): BImu/C500)
University Hospital Executives Council, 1932-1944 (Boxes 14- 16)
Hospital School for Patients, 1923-1950 (Boxes 17-18)
Nursing, 1965-1986? (Box 38)
Clinical Department Minutes, 1990-1995 (Boxes 101- 102)
Medical Staff and House Officer Data, 1922-1989 (Boxes 104- 105)
Architectural drawings, University Hospital, 1921 (UNBOUND RECORDS (OUTSIZE): Bimu/C500)
Registration Books, 1923-1975 (33 BOUND VOLUMES) (OUTSIZE)
HOSPITAL BUILDINGS
Architectural Drawings (Replacement Hospital) (Box 40-48 CLOSED)
Architectural Drawings, University Hospital, 1921,(Outsize folder, BImu/C500)
Replacement Hospital Project, 1970-1984 (Boxes 28-34, 39, 49
PHOTOGRAPHS (Nursing Services) (Box 38)
the University of Michigan Hospitals records include administrative correspondence and topical files; committee files; ward reports and other case records; annual reports of hospital departments; records of hospital activities, and clippings
Subjects:
Hospitals--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Medicine--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Nursing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Nurses--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Hospitals.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan. Replacement Hospital Project.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.; Peterson, Reuben, 1862-1942.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Hospitals.; Hospitals--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Medicine--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.; University of Michigan. Hospitals.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Hospital Administration
  The Hospital Administration series (66 linear feet) contains the records of various directors of the University of Michigan Hospitals, as well as the executive boards and councils. This series is broken up into 8 subseries, each one focusing on a different administrator or committee. Included amongst the administrators are some of the directors, executive directors, associate directors, and assistant directors.
  The Dalston, Jeptha W. subseries (1 linear foot) contains documentation from Dalston's time as the executive director of the hospital system, from 1975 to 1985. This subseries contains a volume of Dalston's correspondence. More records relating to Dalston can be found within the subseries of his successor, John Forsyth.
  The Executive Director's Council subseries (4 linear feet) contain records from the Executive Director's Advisory Council, as well as the similar Executive Director's Council. Included within this subseries are mainly the meeting minutes of these administrative councils as well as other project files. This subseries contains records from 1980 to 1995 and is arranged chronologically.
  The Forsyth, John subseries (29 linear feet) makes up a bulk of the Hospital Administration series. These materials contain records from Forsyth's time as the Executive Director of the Hospitals, between the years 1985 and 1996. This subseries documents the full range of activities in which hospital executives participated in the 1980s and 1990s, including affiliations, negations, and merger talks with other local hospitals as well as with the University of Michigan Medical School, relations with the state of Michigan, the development of a health maintenance organization (HMO), and financial and strategic planning for a major medical institution. Records relating to hospital departments contain some annual reports as well as full-scale reviews of the departmental programs. Some of the materials in this subseries also contain documentation of some of projects and actions performed by Forsyth's predecessor, Dalston.
  The Haynes, Harley subseries (4 linear feet) consists of records relating to the actions of the Hospital Director (precursor to the role of executive director) from 1924 to 1945. This subseries is completely comprised of director's correspondence, which is arranged alphabetically by topic.
  The Howe, Arlene subseries (3 linear feet) contains material from 1973 to 1978, in which she spent time as the Assistant Director of the Hospitals. Topical files are contained within the subseries, and are arranged alphabetically. They include information on the various projects that Howe took part in, many of them concerning the construction of some of the hospital buildings. There are also committee meeting minutes that Howe was involved with, documenting building renovations and space allocation.
  The University Hospitals Executive Board (17 linear feet) subseries consist of materials from the Executive Board, along with related administrative committees including the Executives Council, Executive Staff, Board in Control, and Executive Board. The materials range from 1919 to 1996 and mostly made up of the minutes from these board meetings and executive directories.
  The Warren, Larry subseries (3 linear feet) covers the years 1996 to 2006 during his time as the Executive Director of the Hospitals. The subseries is primarily made up of videotapes from the Executive Director's Forum as well as volumes of Warren's correspondence.
  The Zugich, John subseries (5 linear feet) consists of the topical files of the Associate Director of the Hospitals during the mid-1970s. Materials include records of hospital projects, including surveys and studies, which Zugich took part in. This subseries is arranged alphabetically.
  - Dalston, Jeptha W.
    - Correspondence June 1985-October 1985, 1 volume (Box 106)
  - Executive Director's Council
    - Executive Director's Advisory Council (Box 93)
      - January 1980-May 1991 (Box 93)
      - June 1991-December 1994 (Box 94)
    - Executive Director's Council
      - July 1987-July 1991 (Box 94)
      - August 1991-February 1992 (Box 95)
      - March 1993-January 1995 (Box 96)
  - Forsyth, John
    - Executive Director's Forum 1993-1994, 1 folder (Box 96)
    - Correspondence (Box 102)
      - 1983-1986, 5 volumes (Box 102)
      - 1987-June 1989, 5 volumes (Box 103)
      - July 1989-1992, 9 volumes (Box 104)
      - 1993-1995, 9 volumes (Box 105)
      - 1995 (cont.) (Box 106)
      - January 1996-August 1996, 1 volume (Box 106)
    - Accreditation Council for Graduate Medical Education (ACGME) 1985-1990 (Box 107)
    - AIDS Consortium of Southeast Michigan 1988 (Box 107)
    - Ambulance Service (Box 107)
    - American Red Cross 1981-1990 (Box 107)
    - Arterial Anchor Bandage-Clinical Trial 1990 (Box 107)
    - Association of Academic Health Centers 1983 (Box 107)
    - Audits
      - Ford Motor Company -- Hospital Use and Cost Profiles 1985-1990 (Box 107)
      - General Motors 1989 (Box 107)
    - Affiliated Hospitals
      - Beaumont Hospital (Box 107)
      - Beyer Memorial Hospital (Box 107)
      - Blodgett Hospital (Box 107)
      - Catherine McAuley Health Center (Box 107)
      - Chelsea Medical Center/Community Hospital (Box 107)
      - Chelsea Arbor Treatment Center (Box 108)
      - Detroit Medical Center (Box 108)
      - Foote Hospital (Box 108)
      - Henry Ford Hospital (Box 108)
      - McPherson Health Center (Box 108)
      - Oakwood Hospital (Box 108)
      - Providence Hospital (Box 108)
      - VA Hospital (Box 108)
    - Blue Cross/Blue Shield of Michigan
      - Centers of Excellence 1986 (Box 108)
      - Correspondence -- General 1982-1990 (Box 108)
      - Participating Hospitals Agreement (PHA) Advisory Committee 1990 (Box 109)
      - Physician Reimbursement -- "I-75 Corridor" Issue (Box 109)
      - Prospective Budget Review 1988 (Box 109)
      - The Responsible Use System of Treatment (TRUST) Program 1984-1986 (Box 109)
    - Checklist for Jehovah's Witness Cases and Guardianship Under Michigan Law, circa 1979 (Box 109)
    - Committees and Chiefs of Service, circa 1991 (Box 109)
    - Commonwealth Fund Task Force (Box 109)
    - Diagnosis Related Group (DRG) Data (Box 109)
    - Emergency Medicine Residency 1990 (Box 109)
    - Employee Bonus ("Million Dollar Committee") 1987 (Box 109)
    - Employee Letters (Box 109)
    - Employee Meetings/Breakfasts 1985-1991 (Box 109)
    - Exchange Cart System (Box 109)
    - Exchange Services Agreement 1985-1987 (Box 109)
    - Exchange Services Agreement 1988-1990 (Box 110)
    - Executive Officers Retreat (Box 110)
    - Extra-Corporeal Membrane Oxygenation (ECMO) 1986 (Box 110)
    - Finances
      - Financial Reports 1979-1990 (Box 110)
      - Management Financial Performance Reports 1983-1987 (Box 110)
      - Monitrend Reports 1986 (Box 110)
      - Patient Activity Reports and Budgets 1984-1988 (Box 110)
      - Reimbursement & Rate Setting (Box 110)
      - Retrospective Case Mix Reporting 1984-1988 (Box 110)
    - Fire and Safety Inspections (Box 110)
    - Foreign Medical Graduates (Box 110)
    - Friends of the University of Michigan Hospitals (Box 110)
    - Galens Medical Society 1990 (Box 111)
    - Glenwood Group Home 1986 (Box 111)
    - Goals and Objectives 1982-1989 (Box 111)
    - Graduate Medical Education (GME) 1985-1990 (Box 111)
    - Greater Detroit Area Hospital/Health Council 1981-1990 (Box 111)
    - Health Care Advisory Board (Box 112)
    - Health Care Forum 1990 (Box 112)
    - Health Care Network 1986 (Box 112)
    - Health Maintenance Organization 1984-1990 (Box 112)
    - History
      - Medical School and University Hospital ("Historical Background: The Medical School and University Hospital, University of Michigan. The First Hundred Years."), circa 1971 (Box 112)
      - Replacement Hospital Project (Jeptha Dalston's Notes) 1986 (Box 112)
    - Holiday Planning 1982-1983 (Box 112)
    - Home Care Nursing 1983-1984 (Box 112)
    - Hospice 1983-1984 (Box 112)
    - Hospital Association Political Action Committee (HAPAC) 1989 (Box 112)
    - Hospital Departments
      - Clinical Affairs 1990 (Box 112)
      - Internal Medicine
        - Cardiovascular Fitness and Sports Medicine (Box 112)
        - Geriatric Medicine 1990 (Box 112)
      - Pediatrics and Communicable Diseases
        - Pediatrics (Box 112)
        - Pediatric Cardiology (Box 112)
        - Pediatric Neurology (Box 112)
        - Pediatric Radiology (Box 112)
      - Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation
        - Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation (Box 112)
        - Spinal Cord Injury Program (Box 112)
      - Psychiatry (Box 112)
      - Radiation Oncology (Box 112)
      - Radiation Therapy (Box 112)
      - Radiology (Box 114)
      - Surgery
        - General Surgery (to 1990) (Box 114)
        - General Surgery (after 1990) (Box 115)
        - Orthopaedic Surgery
          - Sports Medicine Program Proposal 1980 (Box 115)
        - Thoracic Surgery (Box 115)
        - Transplant Center
          - Bone Marrow Transplants (Box 116)
          - Heart Transplants (Box 116)
          - Liver Transplants (Box 116)
          - Pancreas Transplants (Box 116)
    - Hospital Network Membership Corporation 1987 (Box 116)
    - Hospitals -- Miscellaneous Correspondence 1986-1990 (Box 116)
    - House Officers 1981-1990 (Box 116)
    - Housing Bureau for Seniors 1983-1986 (Box 116)
    - Howard Hughes Medical Institute 1984 (Box 116)
    - Huron Valley Ambulance (Box 116)
    - Hyperbaric Oxygen Program 1984 (Box 116)
    - Joint Commission on Accreditation of Healthcare Organizations (JCAHO) (Box 116)
    - Joint Committee on Health Policy (Box 117)
    - M-CARE
      - Agreements 1988-1990 (Box 117)
      - Bylaws 1985-1988 (Box 117)
      - Consultancy 1988 (Box 117)
      - Correspondence
        - General 1987-1990 (Box 117)
        - Porwal/Billingslea Correspondence 1986-1990 (Box 117)
      - Financials 1987-1990 (Box 117)
      - General 1986-1988 (Box 118)
      - Health Care Policies 1986-1987 (Box 118)
      - Historical Perspective 1985 (Box 118)
      - Managed Care 1990 (Box 118)
      - Manuals
        - M-CARE Manual 1984 (Box 118)
        - Facilitator Manual 1985 (Box 118)
        - Procedures Manual 1985 (Box 118)
        - Providers Manual 1987 (Box 118)
      - Members Handbooks (Box 118)
      - Operational Review July 1986 (Box 118)
      - Reports 1984-1985 (Box 118)
      - RFI -- Preferred Provider Organization 1989 (Box 118)
      - Service/Clinic Management Proposals 1986 (Box 118)
    - Med-Inn 1984-1987 (Box 119)
    - Medical School
      - Correspondence from Deans Joseph Johnson and Giles Bole 1989-1990 (Box 119)